所以我们正在取得良好的进展
so we're making good progress
但是我们的服务器还是有点笨
but our server's still kind of dumb
毕竟它只能处理一个请求
after all it can only handle one request
好吧，让我们创建第二个请求
well let's create a second request
我在想这个可能是
I was thinking this one could be for
只是我们野生动物保护区的熊
just the bears at our wildlife refuge
哦，听起来很有趣
oh that sounds like fun
现在在我们这样做之前
now before we do that
让我们打印出请求
let's print out the request
所以我们可以看到它的样子
so we can see what it looks like
在它被路由之前
before it gets routed
所以我们想添加一些
so we want to add some
登录管道，它将是
logging into the pipeline and it's going to be
在零件之后
after the parts
但在路线之前，所以我们将在这里添加一个步骤
but before the route so we'll just add a step here
我要调用函数日志
and I'm going to call the function log
这条管道有什么了不起的
what's cool about this pipeline
设计是我们可以插入
design is we can plug in
任何需要对话图的函数
any function that takes a conversation map
并返回一个对话地图
and returns a conversation map
那么我们可以定义日志
so then we can define log
把它放在这里
just put it right here
这将需要一张 con 地图
it's going to take a co n map
它也必须返回一个
it's going to have to return one as well
在那个管道中工作
to work in that pipeline
然后在这里我将使用 io inspect
and then right here I'm going to use io inspect
我们想打印一张地图
we want to print out a map
所以我将使用检查而不是使用 put us
so instead of using put us I'm going to use inspect
我们想检查那张地图
and we want to inspect that map
现在这将起作用，但我们可以使它更简洁
now this will work but we can make it more concise
因为检查打印数据结构和
because inspect prints the data structure and
还返回给定的数据结构不变
also returns the given data structure unchanged
正因为如此，我们可以删除这条线
and because of that we could remove this line
现在我们只剩下一个
and now we're just left with a
这里有单行函数，还有更简洁的
single line function here and there's a more concise
表示单身的方式
way to represent single
将逗号放在此处的行函数
line functions that's to put a comma here
做后冒号
a colon after do
那么我们可以在这里提出这个
then we can just bring this up here
然后摆脱结束
and then get rid of the end
那么如果我们保存并运行它
then if we save this and run it well
我们注意到我们有
we notice we've got
我们的地图正在打印出来
a representation of our map being printed out
在我们看到回复之前就在这里，所以我们
right here before we see the response so we
看看我们收到了什么请求
see what we're getting in as a request
所以让我们处理另一个获取请求
so let's handle another get request
所以让我们拿我们拥有的那个
so let's take the one we have
并将其更改为斜线熊
and change it for slash bears
好的，我会接受我们的请求
okay I'm just going to take the request we have
和所有这些东西
and all this stuff
我现在只是复制它
and I'm just going to copy it for now
我们会将请求从野生动物改为熊
and we'll change the request from wild things to bears
但是如果我们现在运行它
but if we run it now
好吧，我们之前得到了相同的响应
well we get the same response before
因为我们的路由函数当前返回
because our route function currently returns
只有一个回应
only one response
是的，这两个都是回归熊狮子和老虎
yeah both of these are returning bears lions and tigers
所以要解决这个问题，我们只需看看我们的
so to fix that we'll just look at our
路由功能在这里
route function here
传统的解决方案是使用
and a conventional solution would be to use
一个 if 语句
an if statement
长生不老药它看起来像这样
elixir it looks like this
if do else end
这里没有什么令人惊讶的
nothing really surprising here
所以我们可以看看 co 和 v 它有一个路径键
so we could look at the co and v it has a path key
我们会说这是否等于狂野的东西
we'll say if that equals wild things
那么我们想返回这张地图
well then we want to return this map
否则我们会收到只熊的请求
otherwise we're getting a request for just bears
所以我们会返回一个熊的列表，就像
so we'll return a list of bears which would be like
泰迪烟熏和帕丁顿
teddy smoky and paddington
如果我们运行良好
and if we run it well
这适用于我们的第一个请求
that works for our first request we
取回熊线和老虎
get back bears lines and tigers
因为我们要求狂野的东西
because we're requesting wild things
当我们要求熊
when we request bears
我们回来了泰迪吸烟帕丁顿
we get back teddy smoking paddington
但在长生不老药中你不使用
but in elixir you don't use
如果条件和你一样频繁
if conditionals as often as you would
在命令式语言中，例如 ruby
in imperative languages such as ruby
反而
instead
控制程序的流程更加地道
it's more idiomatic to control the flow of the program
使用模式匹配和函数
using pattern matching and functions
在这种情况下，我们可以使用模式匹配
in this case we can use pattern matching
匹配传入的请求
to match incoming requests
并运行适当的功能
and run an appropriate function
填写响应正文
to fill in the response body
所以我们将有一个名为 route 的函数
so we'll have a function called route
这需要
it's going to take
a co 和 v 作为第一个参数，我们需要它
a co and v as the first argument and we need that
这样我们就可以更新响应正文
so that we can update the response body
然后它会走上这条路
and then it's going to take in the path
在这种情况下，这将是野生的
in this case this one will be for wild things
当该函数运行时
and when that function gets run
当我们想要返回这张地图时
while we want to return this map
然后我们将定义第二个路由函数
then we'll define a second route function
这个也会拿地图
this one will also take the map
但它会有熊的路径
but it will have the path of bears
以及何时运行该功能
and when that function is run
我们想返回这张地图
we want to return this map
所以我们有两个同名的函数定义
so we have two function definitions with the same name
和相同数量的参数
and the same number of arguments
在这种情况下，两个参数
in this case two arguments
用长生不老药的说法
and in elixir parlance
我们将这些称为函数子句
we refer to these as function clauses
如果一个函数有多个子句
and if a function has several clauses
灵药会尝试
elixir will try
每个子句，直到找到匹配的子句
each clause until it finds one that matches
现在这些函数有两个参数
now these functions take two arguments
但在管道路线中通过了一个参数
but in the pipeline route gets past a single argument
对了，这就是这里的功能
con right and that's this function here it
有一个 co 和 v 所以的能力
has an ability of one co and v so
在这里我们不想这样做
inside of here we don't want to do this
我们已经在函数子句中表示了这一点
we've got this represented in our function clauses
所以我们需要做的就是利用这个附庸风雅的功能
so what we need to do is take this one arty function
并调用路由方法
and call a route method
需要两个参数或具有两个能力
that takes two arguments or has an ability of two
所以我们将传递 conv
so we'll just pass along conv
我们还将通过 conv 路径
and we'll also pass along conv path
所以我们有一个艺术功能
so we've got a one arty function
调用两个能力函数
calling a two ability function
当这两个能力函数被调用时
and when that two ability function is called
长生不老药将运行
elixir will run
第一个匹配该模式的函数子句
the first function clause that matches that pattern
所以模式匹配适用
so pattern matching applies
任何时候我们需要将值绑定到变量
anytime we need to bind values to variables
例如调用函数时
for example when calling a function
并将参数传递给它
and passing arguments to it
所以我们要这样调用这个函数
so we're going to call this function like this
co 和 v 将匹配
co and v is going to match that
然后无论路径的文字值是什么
and then whatever the literal value of the path is
我们将在那里匹配第二个参数
we'll match the second parameter there
所以它将对这些字符串进行模式匹配
so it's going to do pattern matching on those strings
它是否有效
and does it work
如果我们运行它，我们会得到泰迪熊
if we run it we get teddy
smoky 和 paddington 的第二个请求和熊
smoky and paddington for the second request and bears
狮子和老虎
lions and tigers
现在 http 请求由它们的路径唯一标识
now http requests are uniquely identified by their path
和他们的方法
and their method
得到帖子等，所以让我们改变
get post etc so let's change
function 子句也包含方法
the function clause to include the method too
是的，我们将方法作为第二个参数
yeah we'll put the method as the second argument
所以这些是begets
so these are begets
把那个也放在这里
put that one down here as well
所以现在这些功能有三个能力
so now these functions have an ability of three
所以当我们在这里调用它时，我们需要
so when we call it here we need to
也通过安慰法
also pass the comfort method
所以现在我们有一个艺术函数调用
so now we have a one arty function calling a
三艺功能
three arty function
所以我们很顺利
so we're on a roll
让我们为大脚尝试第三个请求
let's try a third request this one for bigfoot
好吧，我只是再把这些复制到这里
all right I'm just going to copy these down here again
我们稍后会清理一下
we'll clean this up a little bit later
但现在我们只是在滚动
but for now we're just on a roll
所以我们要
so we're going to
继续这个
keep going with this
而不是熊，我有一个大脚怪的要求
instead of bears I've got a request for bigfoot
现在我们知道我们没有一个函数子句
now we know we don't have a function clause that
匹配此请求
matches this request
所以会发生什么
so what's going to happen
好吧，当我们运行它时，我们得到一个错误，说没有功能
well when we run it we get an error says no function
爪匹配
claws matching
路线三，我们看到路径是
route three and we see that the path is
bigfoot so elixir 试图找到一个匹配的函数
bigfoot so elixir tried to find a matching function
但它不存在
but it doesn't exist
因为我们只匹配野生动物和熊
because we're only matching wild things and bears
现在我们将继续在下一节中修复它
now we'll go ahead and fix that in the next section
但到目前为止我们注意到的一件事
but one thing we've noticed so far
是模式匹配消除了对
is that pattern matching removes the need for
if else 条件
if else conditionals
我们知道我们会处理
and we know we're going to handle
更多请求即将出现
more requests coming up
所以我们不会以这个结束
and so we're not going to end up with this
long fl 条件式
long fl's conditional
相反，我们将使用
instead we're just going to use
匹配这些请求的函数子句
function clauses to match on those requests
那就对了
that's right
相反，我们可以编写简短的声明性函数
instead we can write short declarative functions